<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY mdash          "&#x2014;">
]>

<sect1 id="Formalities">
  <title>Formalities</title>
  <sect2 id="Formalities.Questions">
    <title>Questions</title>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Questions. Please stop me and ask them.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            However, some questions give rise to more questions! These must be deferred due to time constraints.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            "What do you think about the paint job on Russell's Teapot?<footnote>
              <para>
                "If I were to suggest that between the Earth and Mars there is a china teapot revolving about the sun in
                an elliptical orbit, nobody would be able to disprove my assertion provided I were careful to add that
                the teapot is too small to be revealed even by our most powerful telescopes. But if I were to go on to
                say that, since my assertion cannot be disproved, it is an intolerable presumption on the part of human
                reason to doubt it, I should rightly be thought to be talking nonsense. If, however, the existence of
                such a teapot were affirmed in ancient books, taught as the sacred truth every Sunday, and instilled
                into the minds of children at school, hesitation to believe in its existence would become a mark of
                eccentricity and entitle the doubter to the attentions of the psychiatrist in an enlightened age or of
                the Inquisitor in an earlier time." &mdash; Bertrand Russell (1872 &mdash; 1970)
              </para>
            </footnote>

          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            However, <emphasis>please see me after this session, or email me with your question</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="Formalities.Objectives">
    <title>Objectives</title>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What will you take from this?
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Depth versus excitement. Not even Gary Kasparov could teach you to play chess in such a short time-frame.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            But he could certainly plant some seeds!
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Beware of under-qualified internet commentators and snake oil vendors offering misleading advice.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            I am more optimistic than Dijkstra.<footnote>
              <para>
                It is practically impossible to teach good programming to students that have had a prior exposure to
                BASIC: as potential programmers they are mentally mutilated beyond hope of regeneration.
              </para>
            </footnote>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            It is <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> an objective to convince you of the importance of the concepts at
            hand or to present irrefutable and compelling cases &mdash; mostly due to time constraints.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Keep thinking. Keep asking questions.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
